Lalu’s father disagreed and said no: he himself had never studied under a tutor. 
It was through sheer perseverance in his studies and after enduring a lot of hardship that he was a successful lawyer today. 
He wished his son would also study in the same manner. 
Of course, there was one condition. 
A tutor would be appointed for Lalu only when he failed to be the first in his class. 
Though he was relieved at this occasion, Lalu was secretly very cross with his mother. 
The reason was that she had tried to force a tutor upon him and calling a tutor at home was similar to calling the police.